Hello, and welcome back to
another video with ItsDrDan
And what we are going to be looking
at today is the anatomy of the atom.
Specifically looking at
modern nuclear atomic theory.
So we're going to be dissecting what the
atom looks like and how did we get there?
In this video, we're first going
to start with looking at Dalton's
atomic theory, which is what we start
our journey on when we are learning
chemistry of how the atom is observed
and how it has come up in our history.
And the thing is that the atom, the
whole idea with this has actually
come up since the BC error, since the
Greek times, where the word atomos was
originally philosophized that we were made
up of tiny, very, very tiny particles.
So this is not a new concept.
It's been around for a very long time.
It's just, it's been in development
through observations and measurements
and theories across many, many
generations of scientists.
Now with Dalton, his whole idea was that
every single element is composed of tiny
indestructible particles called atoms.
Now, all these individual atoms, they
can come in many different ways because
they all have unique properties.
So for example, if I have a bunch
of atoms of carbon all bound
together under very, very high
pressure, they can make diamonds.
If I have chlorine atoms bound
together, uh, they can, they make gases.
If I have silver atoms all Found together,
they will make metal bars and they all
are very, very unique and have their own
individual properties because they're
made up of that individual particle.
Now, along with that theory, all
atoms of that element, they'll
have their own unique mass.
And they all have very unique
properties, which help them be
distinguished from other elements.
So for example, if I look at
sodium, right, this is something
we've talked about before.
It is an alkali metal.
It is extremely reactive.
We've seen, we've seen videos of
getting thrown in water and exploding.
And even though it is a silver metal,
if I kind of compare that to, let's
say, um, silver, which is also a
silver metal after its namesake.
They might both be silver looking, but
they're not the same element, right?
One sodium, one silver, A G versus N A.
So the atoms, they have
complete different properties.
Sodium, it reacts violently
with water, it'll explode.
Silver if you throw it in water,
well, it's not going to do anything.
It doesn't react, right?
So they have their own unique properties.
So, now, other than them also having
their own unique properties, one
of the important thing about them
is that atoms can combine together.
They can chemically bond.
So in the future, in other videos, you
can see that, oh, they can go through
covalent bonding, ionic bonding, and
really be able to see how do they combine.
Now the thing is, they
combine in, in specific.
ratios, meaning that we have
a law of definite proportions.
It is also known as the law
of multiple proportions.
Meaning, for example, that we
will always have whole number
ratios of atoms bound together.
So think of water, H2O, where
the heck, why do you, have you
heard that your entire life?
Where does that come from?
And that's because if you think of
the molecule, it has two hydrogen
atoms bound to every one oxygen.
It's in a ratio of two to one.
It would not be water if
it did not have that ratio.
Same thing right now as you breathe
out and you feel your breath, right?
What is that?
Well, that's carbon dioxide.
CO2.
For every one carbon, there's two oxygens.
It's once again a whole ratio.
Now, that's not the only
thing that comes out of that.
That law.
You can also see being that H2O
is two hydrogens and one oxygen.
You can look up the masses of each one
of those elements from the periodic
table, and you could also add them up in
order to get their complete atomic mass.
which is very, very
important for molecules.
It's something that's going to be
done a lot in your chemistry course.
So adding up those masses is
important, is an important
skill to really be able to see.
Now, the issue with this, it does
not explain everything about it.
Um, one thing that came up is that
Atoms were originally believed to be
completely indivisible, meaning that
they couldn't be split apart, but that
was found out to not be completely true.
How could you differentiate amongst
these atoms other than properties?
It's not enough.
So there has to be additional theories.
Um, this is where they found out
there was a subatomic particle.
So every atom is built up of protons,
neutrons, and electrons to help understand
what these, what these atoms look like.
When you learn how to, how to read your
periodic table, how to actually see how
to, how all these are represented, you
will, you learn about these particles.
They still have the same letters.
They do not have a charge.
Um, Electrons, so if you had a
positive, a neutral, what's left is your
negatively charged particle, electrons.
So you have three different
charges that are available to you.
So every single element is
made up of atoms, and every
atom has protons, neutrons, and
electrons that set them apart.
Now, before we can really look
into this, we have to, how, how
do we put them all together?
They all jammed in the
same location in this atom.
How are they all arranged?
Well, it all came down to essentially
physicists really for a good part of a
century, trying to really get an idea
of, well, how do, how do charges behave?
And the easiest way to think
about it is think of magnets.
So, as a kid, at some point in your
life, you probably played with magnets
and you tried to push them together
and no matter what, they would always
slightly repel each other until
eventually the opposite poles would be
touching each other and be connected.
Um, this is where the idea of like
charges repel each other, meaning
that if you try to push two positive
parts together, no matter what,
you just can't seem to touch them.
Same with negative, uh,
two negative charges.
Um, the reason is, is they require a lot
of energy for them to touch each other.
They, they don't want to, right?
They don't want to be near each
other, no matter what you do.
Now, another thing that comes
up is opposites attract, right?
So that's something we've hear
our entire lives around romance.
And it's, and it's even true down to the
physical setting into your chemistry.
It's inside of your atomic
DNA, I guess as well.
And that's a positive and a negative
are attracted to each other when they
are attracted, they release energy.
So it's favorable releasing
energy is easier to do.
Um, now when you have a positive
charge and a negative charge.
The sum of those, so if you think
of plus one, say, so if you have
one minus one, what do you get?
Well, you'd get zero, right?
So the idea is that you'll
have a neutral particle.
So keep these in mind, right?
Positives and negatives are attracted
because this is going to define
a lot of our chemical bonding.
And on top of that, the idea of having a
neutral particle is very, very important.
Now, how exactly can we try to figure
out How, how the atom is looking?
Well, this is something that required
many generations of scientists
to figure out the major portions.
So the first part of nuclear
atomic theory, so NAT, how
exactly did it all start?
Well, most of it started around
Thompson, who originally figured
out, who discovered that there
were particles that being emitted.
By gaseous atoms, so what he did is he
made what is a cathode ray tube and to
think of what is a cathode ray, um, if you
haven't had an old fashioned television
or maybe an old radio, think of maybe neon
lights, uh, so if you have like a neon
sign that you see like outside of a bar or
a store, right, that excited excitement,
excited energy that's in there, you
see the light that is being emitted.
Now, what happened here is he drilled
a hole in one side of this thing, and
as a result, there's particles coming
out and they were being deflected.
So the thing is, though, the particles,
as they were deflected, they were
going between two charged plates.
One was positive, One was negative.
And if you remember from what I
said before, opposites attract.
You see that the, the stream of, uh,
particles here are getting attracted
towards the positive plate and
they're being repelled away from the
negative plate before they hit the
detector that they're going towards.
So what the heck does that mean?
All right, so that means that our
particle, whatever this is, is negative.
So what particle was negative before?
Those were your electrons.
So it has to do with
something with the electron.
This was a discovery of the electron.
So at first, they believed that the atom
was mainly this big negative thing so If
essentially there was all this negative
atoms and scientists believed and they
knew that atoms were neutral So, how
can one explain the existence of the
negative charges that he was finding?
Well, if there's a negative charge there
must also be a positive charge So this is
where the plum pudding model came from.
Don't ask me for how the name came
up, but essentially the way that he
originally believed that the atom existed
at the time was that electrons were
embedded in a sphere of positive charge.
Okay.
So being, there's all these
electrons that he could see that
were getting repelled, they had to
be embedded in this positive sphere.
All right.
You have this idea.
Okay.
Let's test it.
So this is your hypothesis.
How can you test this?
Well, the way that he decided,
alright, well, if I want to prove my
idea that this plum pudding model is
real, if there's this evenly spread
out electrons across this big sphere
of positivity, that means that this
thing, this atom is mainly empty.
That there should not really be that much
Inside of the material that if I were
to shine, let's say a light through it.
Well, let's say if I put radiation
through, let's say a very thin gold
foil or some kind of foil, then all the
electrons should just go straight through.
Well, all the, uh, what happened was
when all the radiation got shot at this
very, very tiny gold foil, rather than
everything just passing through because
it's going to be this low density
environment, you saw the opposite.
A lot of it passed through, as you
can kind of see in this picture, but
a lot of things were deflected, and in
fact, some of the actually shot, some
of the particles actually shot back,
meaning they were deflected backwards.
So how is that possible?
How could it possibly deflect back
if this big pudding model is all
these little particles and they're
very disperse, there's nothing
really in it, so what does that mean?
What could they possibly be hitting like
a brick wall and getting reflected back?
So what this suggested is that
inside of the atom there is an
area of very, very high density.
the idea that there is a nucleus
with inside of your atom.
So this is where the
beginning really all started.
The atom has a nucleus.
Which inside of that
nucleus contained almost 99.
9 percent of the mass of the atom.
And the rest of it is all mainly
empty space all around the outside.
So, this is where many other
experiments would come into play to
really try to further define this.
But to save us for the time and we only
really want to know about the basics.
There were many experiments to figure
out the rest, but let's just go through
what exactly the anatomy looks like.
This did take observations,
it took measurement to really
try to build an understanding.
So the first thing is, there's a nucleus.
So in the middle of the nucleus
contains protons and neutrons.
This contains almost all
of the mass of the atom.
It's about 99.
9 percent of that mass.
Now outside of the mass is
where the electron cloud is.
So the electron cloud is generally where,
so it's where the electrons can be found.
These things are very, very light.
They are very dispersed, um, and they
can be, they have the probability of
finding them here within their orbits
is somewhere in this general region.
Now, what's the size that
we're talking about an atom?
Well, essentially, the size of a
hydrogen atom is around 100 picometers.
Now, if you think of pico as
one of your prefixes, that's
10 to the negative 12 meters.
So, very, very, very tiny.
So, to kind of help you put that on the
scale of how small we're talking about,
it's probably about maybe trying to put
a Probably the nucleus would be In the
electron cloud, so if you think of the
football field, that would probably be
an electron cloud if I put a penny in
the middle of it, that's your nucleus.
So, the ratio of sizes that we're talking
about is really, really tiny, and then,
you know, if we have one football field,
that would be like, probably finding that
football field in the size of the earth.
It'd be very, very, very, very small.
Um, so, notice where all
the subatomic particles are.
In the nucleus, we have essentially All
the protons, all, all of the neutrons.
And then the electron cloud
is all the negative portions.
Overall, everything is negative.
Now, what about our, what about the rest?
What else can we get from all this?
Well, the size is very, very tiny.
So the nucleus takes up a very,
very tiny percentage of it.
And this is mainly all empty space.
So those are all like the main takeaways
here when we're trying to summarize
exactly what it is that we're seeing.
Um, that the atom, all of the, all
the mass is mainly in the center,
mainly all those neutrons and
protons, electrons, all mainly empty
space and overall atoms are neutral.
So from there, what can
we really get from that?
Well, when it comes to mass, well,
In order to find the mass of any
of the isotopes or atoms that we're
going to be looking at, what we can,
what we are going to do is define
a new scale for ourselves, which is
atomic mass units, or AMU for short.
Being that the protons, electrons, and
neutrons, there's their mass and size.
is extremely tiny.
They're 10 to the negative 27 kilograms.
I don't want to write
that every single time.
So what they did, scientists have
done, is to find a new system so every
proton is equivalent to one amu and
every neutron is also equivalent to
one amu if you just use one sig fig.
So when we're adding up masses we
just add up the protons and neutrons.
We do not worry about the electrons.
So why can we not worry about them?
Well, notice how the
difference of size here.
So that ratio is about a ratio about 1800.
And it's, that's a, it's huge.
That's a very, very large difference.
Meaning that you can ignore the
amount of mass that is there.
You don't have to worry about
it when that's being calculated.
Now the charges, that is very important.
Remember, plus one for protons,
minus one for electrons, when you
are figuring out your charges.
And neutrons are always neutral.
Um, so this is the general idea
of trying to look through all,
all of these different species.
Now, what the last important
point is really focusing on what
the importance of protons are.
So one thing that you'll notice that the
periodic table is organized by atomic
number, and I'll say this in many videos,
that's extremely important, because
the atomic number, which is listed
on top of any one of these elements,
it's what tells you how many protons
something like gold has, for example.
Gold has 79 protons.
Therefore, it has 79
protons in its nucleus.
Now, so that means that any single
atom that you ever will find of gold
will have 79 protons no matter what.
Or, it would not be gold.
So, all, every element has to have
its number of protons in order
to be identified as that element.
So when we're talking about
changing charges, which we'll be
doing a lot in the future, um,
we never change the proton count.
We only ever change electrons.
So keep that in mind, right?
So the other thing to remember too
is, all right, well, if I can figure
out my number of protons from the
atomic number, we can also figure
out how many electrons we have.
And that's because.
Every single one of these
species are neutral.
So if I have 79 protons of gold,
I would have 79 electrons as well.
Now, we can also do this
for other elements too.
So if I have carbon, right,
carbon has an atomic number of 6.
So it has 6 protons, therefore it
has 6 electrons because it's neutral.
Same thing if I want to look at,
let's say, something like sulfur.
Sulfur, if you look it up on your
periodic table, It has 16 protons.
So how many electrons would it have?
It's 16, and that's how we
determine, um, exactly what
species that we have in all these.
Now, all the elements that we, we have
right there with all their properties
and all their protons, right, we can
see them all in the periodic table.
They all are identified by their
chemical symbols, so all their
one and two letter abbreviations.
Many of these are based on Um, How you can
spell them, right, when you're trying to
identify exactly what it is that they are,
but some of them are, are not so obvious.
Some of them might be like off of Greek
or Latin or all kinds of different names.
But we're going to be learning all about
them and trying to identifying them by
their protons, electrons, neutrons, and
counting all those different species.
Alright, this is the end of this video.
I hope that this helped you a little
bit more understanding kind of some of
the ideas of where all this came from.
Biggest thing takeaway is knowing
how that the atom has a nucleus which
has protons and neutrons Surrounded
by electrons, which we will learn
how to organize in other videos.
Thank you so much for listening
I hope this video helped and
I will see you all later.
Bye now